Suchismit **Mahapatra**

Amobee Research, Redwood City, CA 94063

□716-435-8865 | Suchismi@buffalo.edu | #https://schrilax.github.io/ | □suchismit | ﷺ schrilaxs | Suchismit

About Me

I am a Research Scientist with Amobee, applying different Machine/Deep Learning and NLP techniques to solve related problems. I completed my PhD with the Machine Learning & Data Science Research group at University of Buffalo. I have 8+ years of research and 5 years of developer experience during which I have been exposed and worked on a variety of problems.

Research Interests ___

My research focuses on designing and implementing novel algorithms which enable large-scale learning and includes:

- Machine/Deep Learning
- Natural Language Processing (NLP)

- Deep Graph/Geometric Learning
- Nonlinear/Distributed Optimization

Academic Background _____

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

April 2012 - June 2018

September 2010 - June 2012

- Topic: Scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods for streaming data. 🚨 🔁
- Advisors: Varun Chandola, Nils Napp & Jaroslaw Zola | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 (Transcript)

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

Buffalo, NY

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Topic: A Cold Start Recommendation System Using Item Correlation and User Similarity.
- Advisor: Rohini Srihari | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 | Department rank: 1 out of 555 (Transcript)

National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

Rourkela, India

B.Tech. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

August 2001 - May 2005

- Specialization: Discrete Mathematics and Algorithms
- Cumulative Score: 77% (First class with Honors)(Transcript) | Joint Entrance Exam Rank 22 out of 400,000

2021	Became a reviewer for ACL 2021, NeurIPS 2021 and ICLR 2022.	Sunnyvale, CA
2020	Became a reviewer for EMNLP 2021, ICML 2021 and ICLR 2021.	Sunnyvale, CA
2020	Was invited to and attended the prestigious Theory of Reinforcement Learning program.	Berkeley, CA
2019	Became a reviewer for ICML 2020.	Palo Alto, CA
2019	Was invited to and attended the prestigious Foundations of Deep Learning program.	Berkeley, CA
2017	Won a NSF Junior Researcher Award to attend CBMS Conference on Sparse Recovery.	Las Cruces, NM
2016	Became a NVIDIA GPU Educator.	Santa Clara, CA
2015	Won a NSF Student Travel Award to attend IEEE Big Data 2015.	Santa Clara, CA
2013	Won a rare Research Assistant-ship covering my second year as a Masters student.	Buffalo, NY

Skills & Proficiencies _____

Python | PyTorch | TensorFlow | Keras | C/C++ | Apache MapReduce | Scala | CUDA | Hive

Research Experience _____

Amobee Research

SCIENTIST I

Redwood City, CA March 2020 - Present

• Developed a novel bidding strategy based on Win Price (WP) estimation - Developed and productionized a novel bidding strategy using nonlinear ML based approaches for estimating WP.

- Built a Factorization Machine (FM/FFM) based ML pipeline for usage in production
 - Led efforts to build a FM/FFM based ML pipeline using a novel sparse matrix formulation that can handle high modality features.
- Incorporating user embeddings into existing ML/DL models to improve performance
 - Trained BERT/GAN based generative models to construct user embeddings for usage by our existing models.

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST

July 2018 - December 2019

- Improve Click-through and Sales prediction
 - Enhanced existing production Click-through and Sales prediction pipeline using nonlinear ML techniques. Improved stability of our new models significantly from +50% to +5%. A/B test using new models resulted in +3-6% uplift in long-term RexT on all platforms.
- Theoretical aspects of Deep Learning (working with Noureddine El Karoui)
 - Working towards understanding kernel and manifold specific aspects of theoretical deep learning.
- Resolving the posterior-collapse issue in Seq2Seq learning
 - Developed a quantization based approach towards resolving the posterior-collapse issue. 🔼

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

January 2018 - May 2018

- · Kernel Manifold Learning (worked with Varun Chandola)
- Developed novel Manifold Learning techniques motivated from Gaussian Processes. 🔼

Criteo Research Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

May 2017 - December 2017

- · Cross-domain Query-Product (QP) modeling (worked with Suju Rajan)
 - Developed a robust QP model across retailer domains via Domain Adaptation and Optimal Transport based approaches. 🖪

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT January 2017 - May 2017

- Representation learning via DL/NLSDR methods (worked with Varun Chandola / Nils Napp / Jaroslaw Zola)
- Interpreting complex nonlinear processes using DL/NLSDR methods. 🔁 🛗 🛗

BD Biosciences San Jose, CA

MACHINE LEARNING ALGORITHM DESIGN INTERN

- Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry (FC) data
 - Upscaled BD's clustering framework for high dimensional FC data upto ~16x. 🔼 🚨

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

June 2013 - December 2015

June 2016 - August 2016

- Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction (worked with Varun Chandola / Jaroslaw Zola / Nils Napp)
- Developed scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods in a streaming setting.
- Social Network Modeling (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed the xKPGM model for social network modeling. 🔼

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

June 2011 - August 2012

- Localization via Entropy Reduction (worked with Robert Platt)
 - Developed a novel active localization technique via sequential reduction of entropy using OpenRAVE/ROS. 🔼 🛗

Publications

- 1. Interpretable Graph Similarity Computation via Differentiable Optimal Alignment of Node Embeddings. K. Doan, S. Manchanda, S. Mahapatra and C. Reddy. (To appear in SIGIR 2021)
- 2. Discretized Bottleneck in VAE: Posterior-Collapse-Free Sequence-to-Sequence Learning. Y. Zhao, P. Yu, **S. Mahapatra**, Q. Su and C. Chen. 2020 (Preprint available)
- 3. Learning Manifolds from Non-stationary Streaming Data. S. Mahapatra and V. Chandola. 2019 (Preprint available)
- 4. S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. **S. Mahapatra** and V. Chandola. Proceedings of 5th IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2017
- 5. Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. **S. Mahapatra**, F. Schoeneman, V. Chandola, J. Zola, N. Napp. Proceedings of SIAM Data Mining Conference, 2017
- 6. Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. **S. Mahapatra** and V. Chandola. Proceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2015.

Additional Certifications/Projects

- NLP certification from NVIDIA Deep Learning Institute 🛕 | Full Stack Deep Learning certification 🛕
- Coursera Mathematics/ML/DL certifications D <a
- Developed ElGooG A search engine using ~100000 TREC documents as corpus (won the NTipS 2010 competition) 🔼